Theodore "Ted" Amar Lyons papers, Inclusive: 1925-1996, undated, Bulk: 1925-1949, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Theodore "Ted" Amar Lyons papers
Inclusive: 1925-1996, undated, Bulk: 1925-1949, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
1485
Lyons, Theodore "Ted" Amar
1 document box
The Theodore "Ted" Amar Lyons papers consist of correspondence, literary productions, and photographic materials relating to the Baylor University and Major League Baseball career of Hall of Famer Ted Lyons.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Theodore “Ted” Amar Lyons was born on 1900 December 28 to Asa and Sudie Lyons in Lake Charles, Louisiana. Admitted to Baylor on a baseball scholarship in 1919, Lyons was also the starting center for the Baylor basketball team. After his coach convinced him to try pitching, Lyons’s stellar baseball career began. His Baylor baseball years culminated in a 6-2 victory over the Texas Longhorns in 1923, where Lyons pitched a complete game to claim the Southwest Conference Championship. On July second of that year, Lyons signed a contract with the Chicago White Sox, skipping the minor leagues entirely and pitching in his first major league game the very same day.
According to Chicago newspapers, Ted Lyons quickly became the most popular player on the White Sox team. His career eventually spanned 21 years, and he won 260 games with a team that never finished higher than third in their division. His career included three 20-win seasons, leading the league twice. Lyons was so reliable and popular that from 1939-1942 he pitched almost exclusively on Sundays, the day of highest park attendance. Thus, Ted Lyons became known in baseball as “The Sunday Pitcher.”
In 1942, after a season where he posted an exceptional 2.10 ERA, Lyons left baseball to join the United States Marines fighting in World War II. As a Marine, Lyons served primarily in the South Pacific, notably organizing a baseball camp in the Marshall Islands to spread goodwill with America’s national pastime. After returning to the White Sox in 1946, Lyons pitched one more season before becoming the Sox manager for three years. He was inducted into the Baseball Hall of Fame in 1955.
Ted Lyons never married, and spent the rest of his life back home in Lake Charles, Louisiana. Even as late as 1981 he was receiving hundreds of autograph requests each year. He died on 1986 July 25. His legacy and career as a Baylor Bear and White Sox pitcher make his collection a fascinating study for any researcher interested in Baylor, sports, or twentieth century cultural history.
Scope and Content
The Theodore "Ted" Amar Lyons papers consist of correspondence, literary productions, and photographic materials related to the baseball career of Hall of Fame White Sox pitcher and Baylor graduate Ted Lyons.
Arrangement
Prior to this finding aid the Theodore "Ted" Amar Lyons papers had no organizational order or arrangement. Currently, the collection is organized into four series: I: Correspondence, II: Literary Productions, III: Photographic Materials, and IV: Artifacts.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 1485. Acquired 0-00-00
Related Resources
Related references
Bullock, Steven R. Playing for Their Nation: Baseball and the American Military During World War II. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 2004.
“Lyons, Ted.” National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum. Accessed 2013 November 12.
Karnes, Thomas L. “Lyons, Ted.” American National Biography Online. Oxford University Press, 2000 February. Accessed 2013 November 25.
Karnes, Thomas L. “The Sunday Saga of Ted Lyons.” Baseball Research Journal 10 (1981). Accessed 2013 November 25.
U.S. Bureau of the Census. 1920 United States Census. s.v. “Theo Lyons.” Vinton, Calcasieu County, Louisiana. HeritageQuest Online. Accessed 2013 November 12.
Speck, Carl. “Bears Southwest Champs.” The Baylor Lariat. May 23, 1923, sec. 1. Accessed 2013 November 12.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- Alumni and alumnae.; Baylor University -- Baseball.; Chicago White Sox (Baseball team) -- History.; National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum -- History.
Subjects
Baseball players -- United States -- Biography.; College sports -- Texas -- History.
Genres
Photographic print; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Photographs.
- Correspondence, 1942, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains letters regarding Ted Lyons's career. There are also several letters authored by Ted.
  - Correspondence, 1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Literary Productions, 1925-1996, undated; 2
  This series contains newspaper clippings and other literary productions pertaining to the career of Ted Lyons.
  - Clippings, 1925-1996, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General, 1940-1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Photographic Materials, undated; 3
  General condition: Excellent.
  This series contains original photographs of Ted Lyons.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - Photographs: General, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs: White Sox, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Artifacts, undated; 4
  General condition: Average.
  This series contains a textile square with Ted Lyon's White Sox number, #16, embroidered on it. It appears to be a piece of his jersey. It is attached to a frame with staples.
  - Jersey Number: White Sox, undated (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 1)